<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://srini-ry.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://srini-ry.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-03-28T18:40:58+00:00</updated><id>https://srini-ry.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Nvidia GTC 2024 Keynote</title><link href="https://srini-ry.github.io/blog/2024/Nvidia-GTC-2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nvidia GTC 2024 Keynote"/><published>2024-03-18T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-18T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srini-ry.github.io/blog/2024/Nvidia%20GTC%202024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srini-ry.github.io/blog/2024/Nvidia-GTC-2024/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="jensens-keynote">Jensen’s Keynote</h2> <p>A stadium full of AI enthusiasts while Jensen delivers his smoothest, best keynote speech. The Euphoria was out of the world, something one could witness only in the Silicon Valley.</p> <h3 id="highlights">Highlights</h3> <ul> <li><strong>This is a brand New Industry - Generative AI Industry worth $100 Trillion</strong> , where AI factories (GPU data centers) will be creating specialized Intelligences for different industries/use cases</li> <li><strong>Blackwell</strong> - 30X faster inference than current SOTA Hopper.</li> <li>Nvidia’s entry into <strong>Enterprise IT services</strong>: We are effectively an AI foundry with 3 pillars <strong>NIMS, NEMO ecosystem, DGX cloud</strong>. Partnered with SAP, Servicenow and Snowflake.</li> <li><strong>Project Groot</strong> - General purpose foundation model for humanoid, trained on physically correct Omniverse Simulation.</li> </ul> <h3 id="introduction-and-partners">Introduction and Partners</h3> <ul> <li><strong>This is a Brand New Industry - Generative AI Industry worth $100 Trillion</strong> , where AI factories (GPU data centers) will be creating specialized Intelligences for different industries/use cases</li> <li>Accelerated computing is more important than general computing</li> <li>For simulation, it’s more about acceleration, not about reducing cost. We want to do digital twins - completely simulated</li> <li>Accelerated computing - infra is CUDA GPUs</li> <li><strong>3 partners to accelerate systems and chips</strong> <ul> <li><strong>Ansys</strong> - important partner for sim - with Omniverse - giant install base</li> <li><strong>Synopsis</strong> - CUDA is going to accelerate synopsis software - accelerate chip computational lithography. Next step would be to apply GenAI to</li> <li><strong>Cadence</strong> - Copilots for EDA , chip design</li> </ul> </li> <li>Latest Openai model is 1.8 trillion params - 30-40 billion quadrillion flops needed - 30 billion secs (1000 yrs) needed if you have 1 peta flop. <ul> <li><strong>What we need are bigger gpus</strong> - whole bunch of gpus together. With melanox we built Selene, eos.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h3 id="new-chips">New Chips</h3> <ul> <li>Introducing <strong>Blackwell</strong> <ul> <li>2nd Gen transformer engine</li> <li>ras engine - 100% in system self test</li> <li>secure AI - encryption and tee</li> <li>decompression engine - 800 gb/sec</li> <li>AI super chip</li> <li>5th Gen nvlink</li> <li>2.5 times fpa performance for training. New fp6. New fp4.</li> <li>5x inference token generation capability as hopper</li> </ul> </li> <li>Last 8yrs - we increased AI compute by 1000x. For comparison, compute increased 10x every 5 yrs in the past, following Moores law. Now, it’s 100x every 10 yrs.</li> <li>Nvlink switch chip - 200gbps serdes.</li> <li>New DGX chip - 130tbps - entire internet bandwidth of today - 5000 nvlink cables over 2 miles.</li> <li>Training comparion - <ul> <li>For a GPT MOE 1.8 Trillion parameter model</li> <li>Blackwell needs only 2000 GPUs consuming only 4MW power i.e. 1/4th power to train GPT MOE 1.8T in 90 days. Blackwell gb200 nvl72. Hopper was 8000 GPUs for same 90 days.</li> <li>Blackwell is 30x faster than Hopper for inference. Nvlink is communicating 10x faster.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>future data centers are going to be thought as AI factories - Generating intelligence. Generation of intelligence</strong></li> </ul> <h3 id="science-products">Science products</h3> <ul> <li>Core diff - generative AI for weather prediction. Current ones are 25 km res. Now to 2km res. 1000 times speed and 3 times energy efficient. The weather company partnership.</li> <li>BioNemo - for powerful drug discovery</li> </ul> <h3 id="enterprise-ai">Enterprise AI</h3> <ul> <li>NIMS - Nvidia inference microservice <ul> <li>100s of millions of cuda GPUs install base</li> <li>Chatbots inside nims</li> <li>e g. chip designer chatbot .</li> <li>Nemo microservice</li> <li><strong>We are effectively an AI foundry - 3 pillars nims, nemo microservice, dgx cloud</strong></li> </ul> </li> <li>Team of AI - super AI’s - NIMS</li> <li>internal chatbot use cases <ul> <li>chat with bugs database - with Nemo retriever</li> <li>chat for chip designer.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Diana - digital human nim</li> <li><strong>so many companies - enterprise it industries are sitting on a goldmine - ton of data - if u can convert them to copilots</strong></li> <li>hence, we are working with IT leaders - sap , service now , cohesity , snowflake, NetApp. - working with nims, Nvidia Nemo.</li> </ul> <h3 id="robotics">Robotics</h3> <ul> <li> <p>Physical AI - 3 computers - dgx, ovx, AGX</p> </li> <li><strong>Chatgpt moment for robotics is around the corner</strong>. AGX - SoC - high speed process for ai .</li> <li>what is RL feedback of a robot? - by physical feedback - hence we need Omniverse. Physically accurate sim.</li> <li>Omniverse cloud APIs . Chatusd - Chatbot that understands usd.</li> <li>Siemens partnership - heavy industries. Siemens is building industrial metaverse.</li> <li>Nissan - integrated omniverse - for design, manufacturing , development - common ground truth.</li> <li>Omniverse cloud now can stream to apple vision pro.</li> <li>Everything that moves will become robotic.</li> <li>byd now, Mercedes, jlr - soon. Adopting transformer - Thor AGX system.</li> <li>building the entire stack</li> <li>functional asil d systems</li> <li>1.3M robotics developers - Isaac.</li> <li>Isaac preceptor - incredible soa vision odometry, 3d reconstruction, depth modalities. Isaac manipulator- 6d pose for actuators.</li> <li>a lot of imitation training data. Isaac rl gym. Thor designed for transformer engines</li> <li><strong>project Groot</strong> - general purpose foundation model for humanoid. Isaac cloud - Omniverse, Isaac sim. Trained on osmo. Train Groot in physically correct simulation.</li> <li>Omniverse - Operating System of robotics</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI"/><category term="AI,"/><category term="Nvidia,"/><category term="GTC,"/><category term="Robotics,"/><category term="Enterprise"/><category term="IT"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Highlights and notes from Jensen's Keynote]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tracking Safety - from AVs to the world of LLMs</title><link href="https://srini-ry.github.io/blog/2024/Tracking-Safety-in-the-world-of-AI/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tracking Safety - from AVs to the world of LLMs"/><published>2024-03-10T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-10T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://srini-ry.github.io/blog/2024/Tracking%20Safety%20in%20the%20world%20of%20AI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srini-ry.github.io/blog/2024/Tracking-Safety-in-the-world-of-AI/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="managing-risk-in-deep-tech">Managing Risk in deep-tech</h2> <p>With time, we’re seeing more and more startups and fast paced teams making their mark in the field of Deeptech- the likes of nuclear fission/fusion, space tech, biotech, autonomous vehicles etc. The horizontal mother to all these, is evolving to be the field of powerful AI models,which could influence the development of any of those other fields.</p> <p>Managing risk and ensuring safety is a vital need in this space of powerful technologies, where there is a non-zero probability of threat to human life, if the guardrails are not set properly.</p> <p>There are numerous examples in history we could look at , to learn how the risk was contained in those fields - Airline industry, defence technology etc. but the development track of those were different from the software &amp; AI development practices involved in the modern deep tech efforts. Being agile and build &amp; fail fast is predominant in the culture of many software teams. A clash of this fast paced culture with the inherent safety principles one needs to have, is the challenging task at hand to today’s deep-tech companies.</p> <h2 id="learnings-from-av-and-adas-projects">Learnings from AV and ADAS projects</h2> <p>I’ve been fortunate to have worked on risk management problems of AI systems in the early years of AI being applied to a real world task - driving on public roads.</p> <p>For all the teams I have worked with over the years - be it the regulatory body NHTSA, the Safety teams of the German Automotive OEMs or the Risk teams of Insurance companies; even though the business objectives and timelines differed based on their respective roles in the industry, the common goal has been to come up with an efficient statistical and empirical approach to estimate and contain the risk of Autonomous Vehicle Systems.</p> <p>Whichever method one chooses, what I realized over the years is - measuring risk and creating guidelines for AI and safety-critical systems, is a continuous process that extends even to the culture and development practices of the given organization.</p> <ol> <li>Safety should be inherently built within the design &amp; build culture of every team of the org, not only as an isolated activity</li> <li>It is challenging to balance the activities of fast build vs cautious safety mindset of an team- this is where the mettle of the org is decided</li> <li>Ideally you’d want your core tech/product builders to contribute strongly to the safety framework, as they’ll have significant knowledge of the edge cases of what they have built.</li> <li>Use a sufficiently large scale of data to measure your safety metrics</li> <li>Ensure a way of continously refreshing the datasets with real world deployments</li> <li>Synthetic/Simulated data guided by system experts is another key complement to real world data</li> <li>Drive alignment cross functionally , using simplified equations like Severity * Exposure = Risk</li> </ol> <h2 id="status-of-safety-initiatives-in-the-llm-world">Status of Safety Initiatives in the LLM world</h2> <p>Similar to safety reports released by AV players back in the day, we have preparedness and responsibility reports and frameworks published by the AI orgs.</p> <ul> <li>OpenAI Prepareness Framework (Beta) - A 27 page <a href="https://cdn.openai.com/openai-preparedness-framework-beta.pdf">Report</a> <ul> <li>Simplicity of their scorecard is good - it’s easy to track, forecast and control the threats under various categories.But I also believe it will evolve both in the number of categories and the way risk thresholds are decided in each category. E.g. The inclusion of subject matter experts from the domains of CBRN, is going to be vital to improve the current risk assessment process.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Anthropic’s RSP (Responsible Scaling Policy) - A 22 page <a href="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/1adf000c8f675958c2ee23805d91aaade1cd4613/responsible-scaling-policy.pdf">Report</a> <ul> <li>Their AI Safety Levels (ASL) seem similar to the US government’s biosafety level (BSL) standards. They have classified a model’s potential for catastrophic risk into 5 Safety levels, with higher ASL levels requiring increasingly strict demonstrations of safety.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Tooling Companies like Scale are coming up with safety evaluation benchmarks that could be widely adopted by anyone into the development of powerful AI models. They released a benchmark called <a href="https://scale.com/blog/measuring-mitigating-risk-wmdp">WMDP</a> this March.</p> <h2 id="a-few-teams-to-follow-for-updates-on-ai-safety">A few teams to follow for updates on AI Safety</h2> <ul> <li>OpenAI Preparedness team</li> <li>Anthropic’s Safety team</li> <li>Scale’s SEAL team</li> <li>Center for Governance of AI (Oxford)</li> <li>Center for AI Safety (Safe.ai)</li> <li>U.S. AI Safety Institute Consortium (AISIC)</li> </ul> <p>It is going to be both exciting and inspiring to see how today’s leading AI teams will balance the act of safety and fast paced build, in the coming years.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI"/><category term="AI,"/><category term="Safety,"/><category term="LLMs,"/><category term="Preparedness"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learnings on safety and risk management from ADAS & AV industry, and an analysis of what's happening with LLMs]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Addressing the Why of doing a Startup</title><link href="https://srini-ry.github.io/blog/2021/Addressing-the-Why-of-doing-a-Startup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Addressing the Why of doing a Startup"/><published>2021-06-01T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srini-ry.github.io/blog/2021/Addressing%20the%20Why%20of%20doing%20a%20%20Startup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srini-ry.github.io/blog/2021/Addressing-the-Why-of-doing-a-Startup/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="for-all-those-who-are-on-the-fence">For all those who are on the fence</h3> <p>This is a blog post on how anyone can startup and why I think everyone should do a startup at least once in their lives, which is against the popular opinion that startups are hard and not meant for everyone. Yes, they are hard and it will cause you deep pain when they fail. And fail — 9 out of 10 will. You are playing against the odds. It’s like jumping off the cliff, and trying to build a plane before you land. Yet the pain and struggle you endeavor throughout the course are worth it and serve as a self-realization act. In the end, whether the startup succeeds or fails, you walk into the sunset gaining an unbeatable world view of corporations, people, and life in general.</p> <p>A Startup is like jumping off the cliff and trying to build a plane before you land. But you won’t die in case you crash. You’ll get up and walk into the sunset with a better worldview.</p> <p>Off late, a lot of my friends are planning to start a new venture. Their reasons vary — some want to solve an inherent problem they discovered in their current industry, some want to scale up the niche creative work they already do for a living, while some are just bored /stuck in their jobs and want a way out. It might be the pandemic WFH driving this phenomenon as well — the additional time in everyone’s plate catalyzing a self-awareness mental trip of “what is the purpose of my life”? — which by the way is a great startup inducer.</p> <p>So I’m writing this blog for my friends and beyond, to cover the why of startup.</p> <p>Disclaimer — I’m not a highly successful entrepreneur by any measure, but I’ve been in the field of startups for the last 9 years now, having been a part of 3 new product journeys from scratch, two startups, and one exit (profile here). You can consider me as a budding entrepreneur who’s here for lifelong learning.</p> <h3 id="the-why-before-the-how">The Why Before the How</h3> <p>The question ‘Why’ is a frame of mind and a way of living when it comes to entrepreneurship. So, I’ll start with that Why for this series as well. The details of how can follow, but why should anyone even do a startup first thing in place ? And why do I think, everyone should try it at least once in their life?</p> <p>A typical startup journey is akin to a condensed, roller coaster version of one’s full professional life. You’ll get yourself exposed to all the facets of running a company. You’ll start with an idea, build the prototype, hire your core team members, raise money from investors, identify and sell to your customers and grow your product and business. In a way, a Startup is like a crash course version of one’s professional career. You’ll go through the full cycle in a short period of time.</p> <p>But one could gain all these experiences from a well-designed product management program in a big tech company as well. So, why go through all the hardships, stomach punches, and ramen noodle lunches?</p> <p>I wish I could give you one single reason, but human nature is so complex, that attributing the reasons for starting a new journey to one or two, would be unfair and naive. If you look at Founders who have done this in the past — the reasons come in all shapes and sizes- for purpose-oriented founders, it boils down to a strong purpose of existence, action-oriented founders do one job really well and add scale to it turn it into a startup creating more value, and sometimes it comes down to the basic human traits of greed or fear of missing out. Sindbad the sailor is one very good example of why an entrepreneur goes back to the sea of dangers every single time. Your reason could be any of the above — but a common theme among all the successful entrepreneurs is that they like their struggle. They like their hustle. If you are someone who’s agitated too often with a career or life that has turned too comfortable or complacent, maybe you should startup. If you are someone who’s more ambitious than what a 9 to 5 career can give you, maybe you should startup. If you are a dreamer, you should definitely startup. If you don’t like the establishment, you better break it with a new entity, thought, way of working — i.e. a startup. This holds true for any individual — be it a corporate professional, a student, a government servant, a homemaker, or a retired senior.</p> <p>Everyone should try a startup. This is a gutsy and maybe even a stupid statement to make as per many people. The popular opinion is that startups are hard — they’re not like hiking a mountain in your backyard, they’re like hiking Mt Whitney — you’ve got to come prepared or you may fall and die. Which, in a way is true. But, you won’t actually die, you’d be hit with this terrible, stomach-churning feeling of a bad breakup when your startup fails. And you grow when you live past that failure. The pain and failure are totally worth it, and I’m not being romantic here, just being utterly practical. The experience is sure overwhelming, but when done properly it develops within you a mature world view, a strong perspective of corporations, scale, growth, people profiles, and the two fundamental elements it all comes down to — building and selling.</p> <h3 id="but-what-about-the-2-rule">But what about the 2% rule?</h3> <p>Michael Seibel (YC CEO and partner) says this about the three sets of people — 1% people are truly entrepreneurial and flourish under pressure and uncertainty, compared to being a part of a large organization. Another small percent (say another 1%) are impactful and resourceful in any setting — be it an uncertain startup or a structured establishment. The rest of the 98% are people who need a system to optimize, a working structure which they can improve and grow and it wouldn’t be a good idea for this 98% to do a startup. What he said is true. But I still stand by what I just said — everyone should try doing a startup. You’ll never know if you can succeed and if you’re in the 2% that Seibel said until you try it. You can’t come to a preconceived notion that you belong to the 98% who are better working for established organizations. People say you should ask yourself this deep dive question if you can thrive under uncertainty and ambiguity, to know if you are good for startups. But in my opinion, you wouldn’t know the answer for sure until you are in that situation. A strong motive, inspiration, and drive of succeeding and seeing the change you dreamt of often makes you do things you weren’t previously capable of. You’ll never know until you try. So, don’t sit out and say you’re better off as an audience and not good at playing. Moreover, there are methods and ways to decide when one should close their startup if the hypothesis is failing (yes, that’s an option contrary to the popular opinion of Never Give up) and get back to their normal life. There is always a restart next to the gameover button, after losing the three lives.</p> <p>There is a national and geographical angle to this as well — if I consider specially the case of India, on why it needs startups more than any other populist government welfare schemes today, but may be I’ll address that in a separate blog post.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="startups"/><category term="Startup,"/><category term="YCombinator,"/><category term="Entrepreneurship"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For all those who are on the fence]]></summary></entry></feed>